<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<rss version='2.0' xml:base='/blog.rss' xmlns:dc='http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/'>
<channel>
  <title>Blog</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog</link>
  <description>Occasional Blog Posts</description>
  <language>en</language>
  <item>
  <title>test from prose.io</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/27/test-from-prose-io/</link>
  <description>&lt;h2&gt;test&lt;/h2&gt;




&lt;p&gt;testing&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2014-06-27T00:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/27/test-from-prose-io/</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nitrogen and Phosphorous: once wonder nutrients now threaten aquatic ecosystems</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/19/nitrogen-and-phosphorous-once-wonder-nutrients-now-threaten-aquatic-ecosystems/</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen and phosphorus are indispensable nutrients to crop plants. Their importance in achieving high crop productivity cannot be overestimated. Every year, farmers apply millions of tons of chemical fertilizers and manure rich in nitrogen and phosphorus to improve crop yields; these two nutrients are thus essential for food security.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;While nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) are beneficial for crop production, excess nitrogen and phosphorus act as water pollutants. When too much nitrogen and phosphorus reach water bodies, eutrophication can occur, a situation where the fast growth of algae stimulated by enrichment of nitrogen and phosphorus depletes dissolved oxygen with potentially disastrous effects on aquatic ecosystems. Moreover, high levels of nitrate can also adversely affect human health; they can cause methemoglobinemia or blue baby syndrome, a condition found especially in infants.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2014-06-19T00:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/19/nitrogen-and-phosphorous-once-wonder-nutrients-now-threaten-aquatic-ecosystems/</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Arab Spatial Atlas Tutorial (English)</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/18/arab-spatial-atlas-tutorial-english/</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Tutorial on how to use the Arab Spatial Development and Food Security Atlas, an interactive tool that allows users to click through the Arab world--map by map. Arab Spatial is a startup&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2014-06-18T00:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/06/18/arab-spatial-atlas-tutorial-english/</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beyond 1000 Days</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/05/19/beyond-1000-days/</link>
  <description>&lt;h3&gt;New study shows that growth faltering in children continues after two years of age&lt;/h3&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The following story was originally published on the CGIAR Research Program on Agriculture for Nutrition and Health (A4NH) blog.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The world has rallied around the importance of good nutrition in a child’s first 1000 days – from conception to two years—to set up a lifetime of good health. With momentum from global movements such as 1000 Days and Scaling up Nutrition, it has been well documented that a lack of good nutrition during this window can lead to negative consequences for a child’s cognitive and physical development.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2014-05-19T00:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/05/19/beyond-1000-days/</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>‘Let’s climate proof it’</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/02/01/-let-s-climate-proof-it/</link>
  <description>&lt;h3&gt;The UN celebrates World Day to Combat Desertification&lt;/h3&gt;




&lt;p&gt;As the impacts of our changing climate materialize and intensify, developing countries—and poor people who inhabit them—will be impacted first and to the greatest degree. Land degradation, desertification, and a dwindling global water supply pose substantial threats to livelihoods as well as food and national security.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Today, the United Nations (UN) celebrates its annual World Day to Combat Desertification. This year’s theme, “Land belongs to the future – Let’s climate proof it!” sounds the alarm on the importance of sustainable land management practices within the context of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;One-third of the world’s population currently lives in drylands, and desertification and droughts play a major role in both migration and displacement. According to the UN, 42 percent of the world’s very poor live in degraded areas, which translates to lower agricultural outputs as well as lower incentives for investing in productive technologies. What’s more, as the global population continues to swell, it is estimated that, by 2030, there will be a 50- percent increase in demand for food and a 30- percent increase in demand for water. How can we meet the challenge in the face of dwindling resources?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2014-02-01T00:00:00-08:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2014/02/01/-let-s-climate-proof-it/</guid>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When Wells Fail: Farmers’ Response to Groundwater Depletion in India</title>
  <link>/arabspatialblog/blog/2013/04/19/when-wells-fail-farmers-response-to-groundwater-depletion-in-india/</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Groundwater is the mainstay of irrigated agriculture in India. Hundreds of millions of smallholders depend on it for their livelihoods. These livelihoods, however, face serious threats from rapidly falling water tables in large parts of the country. What do farmers do when the wells run dry?&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;In a recent study, Sheetal Shekhri compares villages in Uttar Pradesh that have access to groundwater at just below eight meters with villages where the groundwater level is just above eight meters.  The comparison is interesting because once the water table goes below eight meters, centrifugal pumps no longer work and farmers have to invest in submersible pumps—a much more expensive technology. The two sets of villages are otherwise quite similar to each other.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;Sheetal finds that the incidence of poverty is significantly higher where groundwater irrigation requires more capital-intensive submersible pumps. Conflicts over water are also more frequent in these villages. Thus, falling groundwater tables can increase poverty even if water is not considered scarce, on average, such as in places like Uttar Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;p&gt;The situation is more dire in water scarce regions of India, like in parts of the Mehsana district in North Gujarat. Here, aquifers are so depleted that digging deeper wells and installing more powerful pumps does not allow to access more water.  Often even deep wells have low and unreliable discharge, brackish water and a high rate of failure. While groundwater scarcity is found in large areas of India, pockets like Mehsana represent the more advanced stages of depletion.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
  <pubDate>2013-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</pubDate>
  <dc:creator>SITE NAME</dc:creator>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">/arabspatialblog/blog/2013/04/19/when-wells-fail-farmers-response-to-groundwater-depletion-in-india/</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
